<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rstudio on Homer&#39;s Academic Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/rstudio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rstudio on Homer&#39;s Academic Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 18:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rstudio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing the Addinplots Package</title>
      <link>/post/2016-03-11-rstudio-addinplots-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-03-11-rstudio-addinplots-installation/</guid>
      <description>This is a quick note for instructors interested in installing the addinplots package.
First of all, you need a recent version of RStudio that enables Addins. At the time of writing this is version 0.99.891.
You&amp;rsquo;ll need several packages from CRAN, so run:
install.packages(c(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shiny&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;miniUI&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Hmisc&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;rstudioapi&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;lattice&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;))  Run this even if you already have some of these packages: you will need up-to-date versions.
The devtools package allows you to install packages from GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on LaTeX Installation for R Studio</title>
      <link>/post/2015-12-19-latex-rstudio-debian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-12-19-latex-rstudio-debian/</guid>
      <description>Introduction These are notes to myself and for colleagues in IT. May they also prove helpful to those who land upon them from Google.
From time to time I have to set up R and the R Studio server, configured in such a way that all users can knit their R Markdown documents to PDF with minimal chance of problems. I assume also that some of those users may wish to use LaTeX for other purposes, so I need to start with a reasonably complete distribution of LaTeX and to be able to install or update specific LateX packages as I discover the need for them.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>