<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homer&#39;s Academic Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Homer&#39;s Academic Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 10:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Guidance on the Madhava Graph Problem</title>
      <link>/post/2017-09-27-madhava-graph-advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-09-27-madhava-graph-advice/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This post provides a bit of guidance for students in CSC 115 who are working on the Madhava Graph exercise in Chapter 4 of the course text.
 As you will recall, the statement of the problem is as follows:
 Recall the function madhavaPI() from Section 3.4.1. Use this function to write a function called madhavaGraph() that will do the following: given a number \(n\), the function uses ggplot2 to produce a line graph of the first \(n\) approximations to \(\pi\) using the initial terms of the Madhava series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demo Sites for Blogdown-ified Hugo Themes</title>
      <link>/post/blogdown-demo-sites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/blogdown-demo-sites/</guid>
      <description>blogdown, Yihui Xie&amp;rsquo;s new Hugo-based R-package for blogging, has begun to take off.
You can create a new site using any Hugo theme, but sometimes you must customize the theme a bit in order to enable certain expected features&amp;mdash;such as MathJax&amp;mdash;that are expected by bloggers who deal in statistics. If you are new to static-site generators then you might prefer to have someone else handle the tweaks for you so you can get to blogging right away.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting on your Github User Page via Submodule</title>
      <link>/post/hosting-on-your-github-user-page-via-submodule/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hosting-on-your-github-user-page-via-submodule/</guid>
      <description>My primary technical blog is hosted by Github through my User repository (homerhanumat.github.io). Recently I switched my generator from Jekyll to Hugo.
From the User repository Github Pages requires that the site be served from the root of the repository (not from docs). Jekyll allowed us to build the site into the root, but Hugo builds into a specific directory, named public by default. Building into the root would look a bit messy, anyway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing the Addinplots Package</title>
      <link>/post/2016-03-11-rstudio-addinplots-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-03-11-rstudio-addinplots-installation/</guid>
      <description>This is a quick note for instructors interested in installing the addinplots package.
First of all, you need a recent version of RStudio that enables Addins. At the time of writing this is version 0.99.891.
You&amp;rsquo;ll need several packages from CRAN, so run:
install.packages(c(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;shiny&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;miniUI&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Hmisc&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;rstudioapi&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;lattice&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;))  Run this even if you already have some of these packages: you will need up-to-date versions.
The devtools package allows you to install packages from GitHub.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RStudio Addin Code-Helpers for Plotting</title>
      <link>/post/2016-01-21-rstudio-addin-code-helpers-for-plotting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-01-21-rstudio-addin-code-helpers-for-plotting/</guid>
      <description>There are many benefits to teaching undergraduate statistics with R&amp;ndash;especially in the RStudio environment&amp;ndash;but it must be admitted that the learning curve is fairly steep, especially when it comes to tinkering with plots to get them to look just the way one wants. If there were ever a situation when I would prefer that the students have access to a graphical user interface, production of plots would be it.
You can, of course, write Shiny apps like this one, where the user controls features of the graphs through various input-widgets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on LaTeX Installation for R Studio</title>
      <link>/post/2015-12-19-latex-rstudio-debian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-12-19-latex-rstudio-debian/</guid>
      <description>Introduction These are notes to myself and for colleagues in IT. May they also prove helpful to those who land upon them from Google.
From time to time I have to set up R and the R Studio server, configured in such a way that all users can knit their R Markdown documents to PDF with minimal chance of problems. I assume also that some of those users may wish to use LaTeX for other purposes, so I need to start with a reasonably complete distribution of LaTeX and to be able to install or update specific LateX packages as I discover the need for them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Easy Start with Jekyll, for R-Bloggers</title>
      <link>/post/2015-12-15-jekyll-r-blogger-knitr-hyde/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-12-15-jekyll-r-blogger-knitr-hyde/</guid>
      <description>Note (May, 2017): The blogging approach described below has been superceded by the Yihui Xie&amp;rsquo;s blogdown package. Consult the blogdown repository and the R Studio webinar.
I would like my upper-level students to get more practice in writing about their data analysis work (well, to get get more practice in writing, generally). Blogging is one device by which students can be motivated to write carefully, with a particular audience in mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tutorial on Writing Simulation Apps in Shiny</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-03-shiny-simulation-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-03-shiny-simulation-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>(Edited November 25, 2015.) I stand in awe of the R wizards who post their latest and greatest Shiny feats on R-Bloggers. It&amp;rsquo;s taken me a while to find my way around Shiny, but at last I feel ready to fill in a few gaps for others who may be just starting out and who aspire to write reasonably involved, user-friendly simulation apps. To make it a bit more fun I&amp;rsquo;ve written it up as an R Markdown document.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Charts in R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2014-09-03-google-charts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2014 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-09-03-google-charts/</guid>
      <description>Introduction An excellent little post (Zoom, zoom googleVis) showed up recently on R-Bloggers. The author Markus Gesmann is the maintainer of the googleVis package that links R to the Google Charts API. My first thought was: could I embed charts like those in R Markdown documents that could knit to ioslides or other formats suitable for use in my elementary statistics classes?
 A quick look at the documentation showed that it’s very easy indeed to do this sort of thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Teach Elementary Statistics With R:  #3</title>
      <link>/post/2014-05-05-reasons-to-teach-with-r-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-05-05-reasons-to-teach-with-r-3/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is the third in a projected five-part series of posts aimed at colleagues who teach elementary statistics. If you teach with R but hesitate to spring such a powerful and complex tool on unsuspecting introductory students—many of whom whom will have had no prior experience with the command line, much less with coding—then I hope these posts will give you some encouragement.
The previous post in this series described R Studio’s package manipulate and its applications in the easy authoring of instructional applets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Teach Elementary Statistics With R:  #2</title>
      <link>/post/2014-04-08-reasons-to-teach-with-r-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 23:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-04-08-reasons-to-teach-with-r-2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is is second in a projected five-part series of posts aimed at colleagues who teach elementary statistics. If you teach with R but hesitate to spring such a powerful and complex tool on unsuspecting introductory students—many of whom whom will have had no prior experience with the command line, much less with coding—then I hope these posts will give you some encouragement.
The first post in this series introduced package mosaic, and promised to review a supplementary package that I and a colleague put together for our own students, but I’ve decided put that off a bit and focus instead on another powerful new tool for statistics instruction: the well-known RStudio Integrated Development Environment for R, and its manipulate package in particular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Teach Elementary Statistics With R:  #1</title>
      <link>/post/2014-04-01-tigerstatsintro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-04-01-tigerstatsintro/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is is first in a projected five-part series of posts aimed at colleagues who teach elementary statistics.
I can’t remember exactly how I first made acquaintance with R, but it’s been an important part of my teaching/consulting life since at least 2007, when I used it for the first time in an upper-level undergraduate statistics class. As of last Fall all of our statistics classes—even the elementary ones—are based on R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About This Site</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>More soon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>