<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R Bloggers on Homer&#39;s Academic Blog</title>
    <link>/aggregators/r-bloggers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R Bloggers on Homer&#39;s Academic Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 20:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/aggregators/r-bloggers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Easy Start with Jekyll, for R-Bloggers</title>
      <link>/post/2015-12-15-jekyll-r-blogger-knitr-hyde/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-12-15-jekyll-r-blogger-knitr-hyde/</guid>
      <description>Note (May, 2017): The blogging approach described below has been superceded by the Yihui Xie&amp;rsquo;s blogdown package. Consult the blogdown repository and the R Studio webinar.
I would like my upper-level students to get more practice in writing about their data analysis work (well, to get get more practice in writing, generally). Blogging is one device by which students can be motivated to write carefully, with a particular audience in mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tutorial on Writing Simulation Apps in Shiny</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-03-shiny-simulation-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-03-shiny-simulation-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>(Edited November 25, 2015.) I stand in awe of the R wizards who post their latest and greatest Shiny feats on R-Bloggers. It&amp;rsquo;s taken me a while to find my way around Shiny, but at last I feel ready to fill in a few gaps for others who may be just starting out and who aspire to write reasonably involved, user-friendly simulation apps. To make it a bit more fun I&amp;rsquo;ve written it up as an R Markdown document.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google Charts in R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2014-09-03-google-charts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2014 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-09-03-google-charts/</guid>
      <description>Introduction An excellent little post (Zoom, zoom googleVis) showed up recently on R-Bloggers. The author Markus Gesmann is the maintainer of the googleVis package that links R to the Google Charts API. My first thought was: could I embed charts like those in R Markdown documents that could knit to ioslides or other formats suitable for use in my elementary statistics classes?
 A quick look at the documentation showed that it’s very easy indeed to do this sort of thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Teach Elementary Statistics With R:  #3</title>
      <link>/post/2014-05-05-reasons-to-teach-with-r-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-05-05-reasons-to-teach-with-r-3/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is the third in a projected five-part series of posts aimed at colleagues who teach elementary statistics. If you teach with R but hesitate to spring such a powerful and complex tool on unsuspecting introductory students—many of whom whom will have had no prior experience with the command line, much less with coding—then I hope these posts will give you some encouragement.
The previous post in this series described R Studio’s package manipulate and its applications in the easy authoring of instructional applets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Teach Elementary Statistics With R:  #2</title>
      <link>/post/2014-04-08-reasons-to-teach-with-r-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 23:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-04-08-reasons-to-teach-with-r-2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is is second in a projected five-part series of posts aimed at colleagues who teach elementary statistics. If you teach with R but hesitate to spring such a powerful and complex tool on unsuspecting introductory students—many of whom whom will have had no prior experience with the command line, much less with coding—then I hope these posts will give you some encouragement.
The first post in this series introduced package mosaic, and promised to review a supplementary package that I and a colleague put together for our own students, but I’ve decided put that off a bit and focus instead on another powerful new tool for statistics instruction: the well-known RStudio Integrated Development Environment for R, and its manipulate package in particular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Reasons to Teach Elementary Statistics With R:  #1</title>
      <link>/post/2014-04-01-tigerstatsintro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-04-01-tigerstatsintro/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is is first in a projected five-part series of posts aimed at colleagues who teach elementary statistics.
I can’t remember exactly how I first made acquaintance with R, but it’s been an important part of my teaching/consulting life since at least 2007, when I used it for the first time in an upper-level undergraduate statistics class. As of last Fall all of our statistics classes—even the elementary ones—are based on R.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>